{
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "The tourists amble along the path. Based on its Latin root, amble means:",
        "options": ["run", "laugh", "sit", "walk"],
        "correct_answer": "walk"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ego dē Olympō ad terram dēscendō. Sum nūntius et deus Rōmānus. Quis sum?",
        "options": ["Mercurius", "Neptūnus", "Mars", "Apollō"],
        "correct_answer": "Mercurius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Based on its Latin root, Spain’s Canary Islands had a large number of:",
        "options": ["horses", "dogs", "pigs", "snakes"],
        "correct_answer": "dogs"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which woodland deity would a Roman call upon while hunting?",
        "options": ["Mars", "Venus", "Bacchus", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
      },
      {
        "question": "Patrōnus sum. In vīllā prope ātrium labōrō et semper scrībō. Multōs librōs et epistulās habeō. Ubi sum?",
        "options": ["in tablīnō", "in culīnā", "in monte", "in flūmine"],
        "correct_answer": "in tablīnō"
      },
      {
        "question": "Why would you use the Latin abbreviation P.S. (post scriptum) in an email?",
        "options": ["to greet the recipient", "to add something after the message", "to introduce the subject of the message", "to provide an example"],
        "correct_answer": "to add something after the message"
      },
      {
        "question": "What did a Roman call multi-level apartment buildings in the city?",
        "options": ["īnsulae", "fora", "templa", "thermae"],
        "correct_answer": "īnsulae"
      },
      {
        "question": "When teachers say “Meā culpā,” what are they indicating?",
        "options": ["They are admitting a mistake.", "It is the end of class.", "There is a new assignment.", "It is time for partner work."],
        "correct_answer": "They are admitting a mistake."
      },
      {
        "question": "Septem nautae <u>ab Italiā</u> nāvigābant.",
        "options": ["around Italy", "to Italy", "from Italy", "near Italy"],
        "correct_answer": "from Italy"
      },
      {
        "question": "Sed <u>hodiē</u> ūnus nauta sōlus est in parvā īnsulā.",
        "options": ["today", "always", "now", "however"],
        "correct_answer": "today"
      },
      {
        "question": "Nauta, nōmine Decimus, <u>est</u> perterritus.",
        "options": ["to be", "are", "was", "is"],
        "correct_answer": "is"
      },
      {
        "question": "Nauta cibum nōn videt <u>et</u> aquam nōn habet.",
        "options": ["or", "but", "not", "and"],
        "correct_answer": "and"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ecce! <u>Magna silva</u> est in parvā īnsulā.",
        "options": ["In a large forest", "A large forest", "Across the large forest", "From the large forest"],
        "correct_answer": "A large forest"
      },
      {
        "question": "<u>Per magnam</u> silvam timidē ambulat.",
        "options": ["Through the large forest", "Near the large forest", "Out of the large forest", "The large forest"],
        "correct_answer": "Through the large forest"
      },
      {
        "question": "Nauta puellam in silvā <u>videt.</u>",
        "options": ["was seeing", "were seeing", "sees", "to see"],
        "correct_answer": "sees"
      },
      {
        "question": "Decimus rogat, <u>“Quid nōmen est tibi?”</u>",
        "options": ["What are you doing?", "What is your name?", "Where are you?", "Where are you going?"],
        "correct_answer": "What is your name?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Decimus rogat, “<u>Ubi</u> habitās?”",
        "options": ["Who", "What", "Where", "Why"],
        "correct_answer": "Where"
      },
      {
        "question": "Tum Decimus rogat, “<u>Habēsne</u> aquam?”",
        "options": ["Where do you have", "Do you have", "Why do you have", "Who has"],
        "correct_answer": "Do you have"
      },
      {
        "question": "Tiberīna respondet, “<u>Ita vērō.</u> Ego et pater aquam habēmus.”",
        "options": ["Hello", "Goodbye", "No", "Yes"],
        "correct_answer": "Yes"
      },
      {
        "question": "Decimus dīcit, “<u>Ego</u> et multī nautae ad Graeciam nāvigābāmus.”",
        "options": ["you", "we", "he", "I"],
        "correct_answer": "I"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the Roman goddess of marriage and the queen of the gods?",
        "options": ["Minerva", "Vesta", "Diana", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Juno"
      },
      {
        "question": "What should you say when leaving a group of friends?",
        "options": ["Cūr?", "Quot?", "Salvē!", "Valēte!"],
        "correct_answer": "Valēte!"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the paterfamiliās in charge of in ancient Rome?",
        "options": ["the household", "the government", "the army", "the gladiator school"],
        "correct_answer": "the household"
      },
      {
        "question": "According to its Latin root, if something is a multi-unit structure, what does it have?",
        "options": ["small units", "square units", "many units", "empty units"],
        "correct_answer": "many units"
      },
      {
        "question": "Solve the following equation: V + V = _____.",
        "options": ["III", "VI", "VIII", "X"],
        "correct_answer": "X"
      },
      {
        "question": "Stellar, solar, and lunar all describe objects that can be found where?",
        "options": ["in caelō", "in silvā", "in rīvō", "in forō"],
        "correct_answer": "in caelō"
      },
      {
        "question": "Why would a worker typically receive a bonus?",
        "options": ["Their work was late.", "Their work was average.", "Their work needed correction.", "Their work was good."],
        "correct_answer": "Their work was good."
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the most popular and largest location for chariot racing in the city of Rome?",
        "options": ["Colosseum", "Circus Maximus", "Forum", "Pantheon"],
        "correct_answer": "Circus Maximus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which god ruled the Underworld and possessed its mineral wealth?",
        "options": ["Mars", "Mercury", "Pluto", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Pluto"
      },
      {
        "question": "What legendary Trojan led refugees from the fall of Troy across the Mediterranean Sea to establish a homeland in Italy?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Achilles", "Hector", "Romulus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
      },
      {
        "question": "What area was NOT physically connected to the Roman Empire by land?",
        "options": ["Hispānia", "Britannia", "Germānia", "Gallia"],
        "correct_answer": "Britannia"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which Latin phrase could you use to encourage someone to hurry?",
        "options": ["cum laude", "e pluribus unum", "nota bene", "tempus fugit"],
        "correct_answer": "tempus fugit"
      },
      {
        "question": "When a list ends with etc., it indicates that",
        "options": ["the list is very important", "the list is complete", "there are more items", "the last item is incorrect"],
        "correct_answer": "there are more items"
      },
      {
        "question": "Solve the following equation: V - I =",
        "options": ["III", "IV", "VI", "IX"],
        "correct_answer": "IV"
      },
      {
        "question": "October, octet, and octave are all related to the Latin word for",
        "options": ["eye", "ocean", "eight", "music"],
        "correct_answer": "eight"
      },
      {
        "question": "When sailors circumnavigate an island, they sail",
        "options": ["across it", "around it", "through it", "under it"],
        "correct_answer": "around it"
      },
      {
        "question": "Mārcus <u>est</u> agricola.",
        "options": ["are", "was", "to be", "is"],
        "correct_answer": "is"
      },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus <u>multōs agrōs</u> habet.",
        "options": ["many fields", "near many fields", "toward many fields", "with many fields"],
        "correct_answer": "many fields"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus per agrōs <u>laetē</u> ambulat.",
        "options": ["happy", "happily", "happiness", "to be happy"],
        "correct_answer": "happily"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus terram <u>arāre</u> temptat.",
        "options": ["to plow", "are plowing", "was plowing", "were plowing"],
        "correct_answer": "to plow"
    },
    {
        "question": "<u>Mārcus</u> semper labōrat.",
        "options": ["Marcus", "with Marcus", "near Marcus", "to Marcus"],
        "correct_answer": "Marcus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus <u>cum familiā</u> in casā habitat.",
        "options": ["his family", "near his family", "around his family", "with his family"],
        "correct_answer": "with his family"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus <u>virīs et fēminīs</u> multum cibum ex agrīs dat.",
        "options": ["a man and a woman", "to men and women", "from men and women", "with man and woman"],
        "correct_answer": "to men and women"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus vītam dūram <u>sed</u> laetam habet.",
        "options": ["not", "and", "but", "because"],
        "correct_answer": "but"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lūcius <u>erat</u> poēta.",
        "options": ["were", "was", "are", "is"],
        "correct_answer": "was"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lūcius cantābat; virī et fēminae Lūcium <u>laudābant.</u>",
        "options": ["were praising", "is praising", "are praising", "to praise"],
        "correct_answer": "were praising"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pecūniam Lūciō <u>dabant.</u>",
        "options": ["They used to give", "You used to give", "We used to give", "I used to give"],
        "correct_answer": "They used to give"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hodiē virī et fēminae Lūcium <u>nōn</u> laudant.",
        "options": ["well", "always", "when", "not"],
        "correct_answer": "not"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hodiē Lūcius <u>prope agrōs</u> per viam ambulat.",
        "options": ["from the fields", "near the fields", "across the fields", "to the fields"],
        "correct_answer": "near the fields"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus aquam ad agrōs <u>portat.</u>",
        "options": ["was carrying", "are carrying", "is carrying", "were carrying"],
        "correct_answer": "is carrying"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus Lūcium videt et rogat, <u>“Quis es tū?”</u>",
        "options": ["Who are you?", "What are you doing?", "Why are you here?", "Where are you from?"],
        "correct_answer": "Who are you?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lūcius respondet, “<u>Ego</u> sum Lūcius.”",
        "options": ["We", "you", "me", "I"],
        "correct_answer": "I"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lūcius rogat, “<u>Tūne aquam habēs?</u>”",
        "options": ["Where is there water?", "Who has water?", "Do you have water?", "Is the water yours?"],
        "correct_answer": "Do you have water?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mārcus respondet, “Ita vērō. Ecce! <u>Potā</u> aquam!”",
        "options": ["To drink", "Drink", "Drinks", "Does drink"],
        "correct_answer": "Drink"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the opposite of the response “Minimē”?",
        "options": ["Salvē", "Ita", "Ante", "Nōn"],
        "correct_answer": "Ita"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a common piece of clothing worn by all Romans?",
        "options": ["taberna", "fenestra", "tunica", "hōra"],
        "correct_answer": "tunica"
    },
    {
        "question": "Based on its Latin root, a constellation is a group of",
        "options": ["birds", "islands", "stars", "ships"],
        "correct_answer": "stars"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fabulous, fable, and fib are all related to the Latin word for a",
        "options": ["story", "spectacle", "valuable object", "library"],
        "correct_answer": "story"
    },
    {
        "question": "An ātrium, a cubiculum, and a tablīnum could all be found",
        "options": ["in vīllā", "in silvā", "in agrō", "in amphitheātrō"],
        "correct_answer": "in vīllā"
    },
    {
        "question": "From this series of odd Roman numerals, I, III, V, _____, IX, which Roman numeral is missing?",
        "options": ["II", "IV", "VII", "VIII"],
        "correct_answer": "VII"
    },
    {
        "question": "What abbreviation indicates that a reader should pay close attention to what follows?",
        "options": ["N.B.", "a.m.", "etc.", "P.S."],
        "correct_answer": "N.B."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is Latin for “out of many, one,” the motto held by the eagle on the Great Seal of the United States of America?",
        "options": ["excelsior", "carpe diem", "in deo speramus", "e pluribus unum"],
        "correct_answer": "e pluribus unum"
    },
    {
        "question": "The three Olympian brothers whose realms were the sky, the Underworld, and the seas were Jupiter, Pluto, and",
        "options": ["Mars", "Neptune", "Apollo", "Vulcan"],
        "correct_answer": "Neptune"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flāvia est <u>parva puella.</u>",
        "options": ["a poor girl", "a smart girl", "a happy girl", "a little girl"],
        "correct_answer": "a little girl"
    },
    {
        "question": "<u>Quārtus</u> est parvus puer.",
        "options": ["near Quartus", "to Quartus", "with Quartus", "Quartus"],
        "correct_answer": "Quartus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pater <u>Flāviae</u> est poēta et pater Quārtī est agricola.",
      "options": ["Flavia", "of Flavia", "by Flavia", "from Flavia"],
      "correct_answer": "of Flavia"
  },
  {
      "question": "Patrēs semper <u>clāmābant</u> et nōn erant amīcī.",
      "options": ["were shouting", "was shouting", "are shouting", "to shout"],
      "correct_answer": "were shouting"
  },
  {
      "question": "Patrēs sunt inimīcī <u>sed</u> Flāvia et Quārtus sunt amīcī.",
      "options": ["and", "not", "because", "but"],
      "correct_answer": "but"
  },
  {
      "question": "<u>Hodiē</u> amīcī in viā per silvam ambulant.",
      "options": ["Today", "Always", "Slowly", "Happily"],
      "correct_answer": "Today"
  },
  {
      "question": "Flāvia et Quārtus flōrēs in silvā sine patribus <u>spectāre</u> amant.",
      "options": ["are looking at", "to look at", "was looking at", "were looking at"],
      "correct_answer": "to look at"
  },
  {
      "question": "Amīcī <u>cibum et aquam</u> portant.",
      "options": ["of food and water", "to food and water", "food and water", "with food and water"],
      "correct_answer": "food and water"
  },
  {
      "question": "<u>Ecce!</u> Flāvia et Quārtus magnum equum in mediā silvā vident.",
      "options": ["Hello!", "Look!", "No!", "What!"],
      "correct_answer": "Look!"
  },
  {
      "question": "Flāvia et Quārtus <u>ad equum</u> ambulant.",
      "options": ["toward the horse", "with the horse", "from the horse", "around the horse"],
      "correct_answer": "toward the horse"
  },
  {
      "question": "Puer equum vocat et clāmat, “<u>Ambulā</u> ad nōs!”",
      "options": ["To walk", "He was walking", "Walk", "They were walking"],
      "correct_answer": "Walk"
  },
  {
      "question": "Equus ad amīcōs nōn ambulat sed ab amīcīs <u>festīnat.</u>",
      "options": ["are hurrying", "was hurrying", "were hurrying", "is hurrying"],
      "correct_answer": "is hurrying"
  },
  {
      "question": "Amīcī <u>ā viā</u> post equum ambulant.",
      "options": ["the road", "away from the road", "down the road", "near the road"],
      "correct_answer": "away from the road"
  },
  {
      "question": "Flāvia rogat, “<u>Vidēsne viam?</u>”",
      "options": ["When did you see the road?", "You don’t see the road, do you?", "Do you see the road?", "And did you see the road?"],
      "correct_answer": "Do you see the road?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Quārtus timidus circumspectat et respondet, “<u>Ego</u> viam nōn videō.”",
    "options": ["you", "I", "me", "us"],
    "correct_answer": "I"
  },
  {
    "question": "Puella rogat, “<u>Ubi sumus</u>?”",
    "options": ["Where is it?", "Where are you?", "Where are we?", "Where am I?"],
    "correct_answer": "Where are we?"
},
{
    "question": "Puer <u>timidē</u> lacrimat.",
    "options": ["fear", "to fear", "fearful", "fearfully"],
    "correct_answer": "fearfully"
},
{
    "question": "Puella aquam <u>puerō</u> dat.",
    "options": ["to the boy", "of the boy", "from the boy", "with the boy"],
    "correct_answer": "to the boy"
},
  {
      "question": "What is the best response to Quid agis?",
      "options": ["Ubi?", "Quot?", "Bene!", "Valēte!"],
      "correct_answer": "Bene!"
  },
  {
      "question": "Where in ancient Rome would you find an atrium?",
      "options": ["on the road", "in a house", "in a forum", "in a harbor"],
      "correct_answer": "in a house"
  },
  {
      "question": "Students attend a naval institute to learn about",
      "options": ["anatomy", "agriculture", "sculpting", "ships"],
      "correct_answer": "ships"
  },
  {
      "question": "Quis est frater Diānae?",
      "options": ["Apollō", "Plūtō", "Mercurius", "Neptūnus"],
      "correct_answer": "Apollō"
  },
  {
      "question": "In which Roman province was the Nile River located?",
      "options": ["Britannia", "Germania", "Aegyptus", "Gallia"],
      "correct_answer": "Aegyptus"
  },
  {
      "question": "If you wanted to encourage your friend to live a full life, you might say",
      "options": ["Minimē", "Ē plūribus ūnum", "Tacēte!", "Carpe diem!"],
      "correct_answer": "Carpe diem!"
  },
  {
      "question": "Which Roman numeral represents the largest amount?",
      "options": ["IX", "III", "V", "VIII"],
      "correct_answer": "IX"
  },
  {
      "question": "What was a common occurrence at the Colosseum?",
      "options": ["poetry performances", "gladiatorial fights", "cold baths", "diplomatic meetings"],
      "correct_answer": "gladiatorial fights"
  },
  {
      "question": "Based on the word’s Latin root, a portable device is easy to",
      "options": ["carry", "throw", "find", "use"],
      "correct_answer": "carry"
  },
  {
      "question": "What animal would typically play a major part in the action at the Circus Maximus?",
      "options": ["elephantus", "equus", "ursus", "leō"],
      "correct_answer": "equus"
  },
  {
      "question": "What Roman god of music was often seen with a lyre?",
      "options": ["Mars", "Mercury", "Apollo", "Vulcan"],
      "correct_answer": "Apollo"
  },
  {
      "question": "Quis est pater Minervae?",
      "options": ["Iuppiter", "Neptūnus", "Saturnus", "Plūtō"],
      "correct_answer": "Iuppiter"
  },
  {
      "question": "A Roman woman would often wear a _____ over her stola.",
      "options": ["tunica", "solea", "toga", "palla"],
      "correct_answer": "palla"
  },
  {
      "question": "It’s time for bed! In a vīlla, where would the father and mother sleep?",
      "options": ["in cubiculō", "in vestibulō", "in tablīnō", "in culīnā"],
      "correct_answer": "in cubiculō"
  },
  {
      "question": "VII et II sunt _____.",
      "options": ["III", "V", "IX", "X"],
      "correct_answer": "IX"
  },
  {
      "question": "If you met Antonia and Aula talking together in the Forum, how would you greet them?",
      "options": ["Salvē!", "Valē!", "Salvēte!", "Valēte!"],
      "correct_answer": "Salvēte!"
  },
  {
      "question": "The words were audible all over the building. Audible comes from the Latin verb meaning to",
      "options": ["see", "hear", "write", "read"],
      "correct_answer": "hear"
  },
  {
      "question": "If you wanted to scare a thief away from your home, which Latin phrase would you put on your door?",
      "options": ["Carpe diem!", "Ē plūribus ūnum!", "Cavē canem!", "Tempus fugit!"],
      "correct_answer": "Cavē canem!"
  },
    {
        "question": "In an announcement of a person’s death, which phrase would you most likely see?",
        "options": ["ab urbe conditā", "mare nostrum", "festīnā lentē", "in memoriam"],
        "correct_answer": "in memoriam"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is not an animal?",
        "options": ["lupus", "porcus", "lūdus", "equus"],
        "correct_answer": "lūdus"
    },
    {
        "question": "The peacock is the symbol of which goddess?",
        "options": ["Minerva", "Juno", "Diana", "Vesta"],
        "correct_answer": "Juno"
    },
    {
        "question": "One who has made a mistake should say,",
        "options": ["Carpe diem!", "Meā culpā!", "Bene!", "Salvē!"],
        "correct_answer": "Meā culpā!"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Latin teacher asking you your name would say",
        "options": ["Quid est nōmen tibi?", "Suntne laetī?", "Quota hōra est?", "Ubi sunt discipulī?"],
        "correct_answer": "Quid est nōmen tibi?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ubi servī cēnam parant?",
        "options": ["in cubiculō", "in ātriō", "in hortō", "in culīnā"],
        "correct_answer": "in culīnā"
    },
    {
        "question": "Based on the Latin root, a person ambling through the woods is",
        "options": ["clearing a trail", "hunting animals", "walking the paths", "calling to a friend"],
        "correct_answer": "walking the paths"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where would a Roman buy new sandals?",
        "options": ["in tabernā", "in cūriā", "in vīllā rūsticā", "in templō"],
        "correct_answer": "in tabernā"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tiber River is located in",
        "options": ["Gallia", "Italia", "Graecia", "Hispānia"],
        "correct_answer": "Italia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Latin class is so much fun! To express your surprise at how quickly it passes, you might exclaim,",
        "options": ["Tempus fugit!", "Annō Dominī!", "Ē plūribus ūnum!", "Et cētera!"],
        "correct_answer": "Tempus fugit!"
    },
    {
        "question": "The teacher said, “That’s a novel idea!” Novel means",
        "options": ["wise", "bad", "dangerous", "new"],
        "correct_answer": "new"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Roman name for the Greek god Hermes?",
        "options": ["Mercury", "Mars", "Vulcan", "Pluto"],
        "correct_answer": "Mercury"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Roman numerals IV + VI =",
        "options": ["VII", "VIII", "IX", "X"],
        "correct_answer": "X"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Latin teacher asking the name of a person in a picture would ask",
        "options": ["Ubi est?", "Quid agis?", "Quis est?", "Estne laetus?"],
        "correct_answer": "Quis est?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who in ancient Rome wore a toga praetexta?",
        "options": ["senator", "mater", "libertus", "servus"],
        "correct_answer": "senator"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the best translation of the Latin motto festīnā lentē?",
        "options": ["hurry slowly", "happy birthday", "time flies", "seize the day"],
        "correct_answer": "hurry slowly"
    },
    {
        "question": "Based on the Latin root, who would be considered urbane?",
        "options": ["a sailor", "a city dweller", "a shepherd", "a nymph"],
        "correct_answer": "a city dweller"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what large amphitheater would the Romans watch gladiatorial fights and animal hunts?",
        "options": ["the Forum", "the Curia", "the Colosseum", "the Pantheon"],
        "correct_answer": "the Colosseum"
    },
    {
        "question": "If a bird flew in a straight line from Hispania to Graecia, it would be flying",
        "options": ["north", "south", "east", "west"],
        "correct_answer": "east"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Latin abbreviation means “and the rest”?",
        "options": ["P.S.", "a.m.", "N.B.", "etc."],
        "correct_answer": "etc."
    },
    {
        "question": "The malevolent king lived in a castle at the top of the mountain.",
        "options": ["old", "wise", "faithful", "evil"],
        "correct_answer": "evil"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which animal has four legs?",
        "options": ["piscis", "avis", "equus", "homō"],
        "correct_answer": "equus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal is associated with the founding of Rome?",
        "options": ["elephant", "rabbit", "goose", "wolf"],
        "correct_answer": "wolf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin phrase ita vērō is the opposite of",
        "options": ["bene", "minimē", "salvē", "grātiās"],
        "correct_answer": "minimē"
    },
    {
        "question": "What main room of a Roman house had an impluvium and compluvium as well as a shrine to the household gods?",
        "options": ["cubiculum", "ātrium", "culīna", "trīclīnium"],
        "correct_answer": "ātrium"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Latin for “in God we hope,” the motto of Brown University?",
        "options": ["in locō parentis", "in tōtō", "in deō spērāmus", "in vīnō vēritās"],
        "correct_answer": "in deō spērāmus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cleopatra was multilingual.",
        "options": ["a lover of many cultures", "a speaker of many languages", "a citizen of many countries", "a woman of many facial expressions"],
        "correct_answer": "a speaker of many languages"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where would a Roman go to shop, to socialize, and to hear speeches?",
        "options": ["Forum", "Colosseum", "Circus Maximus", "Pantheon"],
        "correct_answer": "Forum"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the abbreviation A.D., the letter “A” stands for the Latin word",
        "options": ["Ad", "Annō", "Aut", "Ab"],
        "correct_answer": "Anno"
    },
    {
        "question": "The farmers could not inhabit the rocky coastal area.",
        "options": ["protect", "plow", "clean up", "live in"],
        "correct_answer": "live in"
    },
    {
        "question": "The motto labor omnia vincit best reflects the actions of a Latin student who",
        "options": ["sleeps in class", "always does his work", "misses many days of school", "is friendly to the teacher"],
        "correct_answer": "always does his work"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the abbreviation a.m., the letter a stands for the Latin word",
        "options": ["aut", "ad", "ab", "ante"],
        "correct_answer": "ante"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman god rules the Underworld?",
        "options": ["Neptune", "Mars", "Pluto", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which room of a vīlla would Romans usually entertain friends at dinner?",
        "options": ["ātrium", "cubiculum", "lātrīna", "trīclīnium"],
        "correct_answer": "trīclīnium"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the religious, economic, political, and social center of ancient Rome?",
        "options": ["Forum Rōmānum", "Colossēum", "Via Appia", "Circus Maximus"],
        "correct_answer": "Forum Rōmānum"
    },
    {
        "question": "To which question would “Bene!” be an appropriate answer?",
        "options": ["Quid agis?", "Quid est nōmen tibi?", "Quis est?", "Quis es?"],
        "correct_answer": "Quid agis?"
    },
    {
        "question": "The worker’s <u>per annum</u> income was enough to meet their needs.",
        "options": ["daily", "weekly", "monthly", "yearly"],
        "correct_answer": "yearly"
    },
    {
        "question": "The long snout and watchful eyes of the creature made it appear <u>lupine.</u>",
        "options": ["cat-like", "goose-like", "wolf-like", "cow-like"],
        "correct_answer": "wolf-like"
    },
    {
        "question": "The youth left home in search of <u>pecuniary</u> rewards.",
        "options": ["education", "money", "freedom", "adventure"],
        "correct_answer": "money"
    },
    {
        "question": "The abbreviation N.B. stands for the Latin phrase Notā Bene which means",
        "options": ["Note well", "Make haste", "And the rest", "Farewell"],
        "correct_answer": "Note well"
    },
    {
        "question": "If your older sister says your behavior is puerile, she means you are",
        "options": ["childish", "sad", "clever", "sick"],
        "correct_answer": "childish"
    },
    {
        "question": "Based on your knowledge of Latin, the purpose of a convocation is to",
        "options": ["give people news", "assign people to help", "call people together", "ask people their opinion"],
        "correct_answer": "call people together"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should the class do when the teacher says, “Sedēte?”",
        "options": ["stand", "be quiet", "leave", "remain seated"],
        "correct_answer": "remain seated"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the Roman goddess of wisdom, war, and weaving?",
        "options": ["Juno", "Diana", "Minerva", "Venus"],
        "correct_answer": "Minerva"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where would a Roman typically go to watch chariot racing?",
        "options": ["templum", "Forum", "cubiculum", "Circus Maximus"],
        "correct_answer": "Circus Maximus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Plīnius epistulam <u>stilō</u> scrīpsit.",
      "options": ["with a pen", "for a pen", "of a pen", "a pen"],
      "correct_answer": "with a pen"
    },
    {
      "question": "Est saepe difficile mihi <u>dormīre</u>.",
      "options": ["will sleep", "have slept", "to sleep", "are sleeping"],
      "correct_answer": "to sleep"
    },
    {
      "question": "Amīcus meus ad thermās cum <u>patre</u> vēnit.",
      "options": ["of his father", "for his father", "his father", "with his father"],
      "correct_answer": "with his father"
    },
    {
      "question": "Agricola multās vaccās in agrō <u>cūrābat</u>.",
      "options": ["is taking care of", "was taking care of", "will take care of", "has taken care of"],
      "correct_answer": "was taking care of"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cleopatra erat _____ Aegyptī.",
        "options": ["rēgīna", "rēgīnae", "rēgīnam", "rēgīnā"],
        "correct_answer": "rēgīna"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pater cibum optimum <u>hospitī praeclārō</u> dabat.",
        "options": ["of his famous guest", "to his famous guest", "from his famous guest", "by his famous guest"],
        "correct_answer": "to his famous guest"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tempestās est semper splendida. Heri sōl lūcēbat, _____ sōl lūcet, et crās sōl lūcēbit.",
        "options": ["numquam", "statim", "saepe", "hodiē"],
        "correct_answer": "hodiē"
    },
    {
      "question": "<u>Cantābisne</u> mihi pulchrum carmen post cēnam?",
      "options": ["Will you sing", "Were you singing", "Are you singing", "Did you sing"],
      "correct_answer": "Will you sing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nōmina omnium animālium <u>scīvistī</u>.",
      "options": ["I knew", "You knew", "He knew", "We knew"],
      "correct_answer": "You knew"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trāns rīvum et per silvās ad casam mātris ā casā nostrā prōcēdimus. In this sentence, what is our final destination?",
        "options": ["a river", "the woods", "mother’s house", "our house"],
        "correct_answer": "mother’s house"
    },
    {
        "question": "“<u>Nōlī</u>, pater, in ātriō <u>clāmāre</u>! Īnfāns dormit!”",
        "options": ["He shouted", "Don’t shout", "Why not shout", "No one shouts"],
        "correct_answer": "Don’t shout"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fīlius meus in peristȳliō <u>quiētē</u> legit.",
        "options": ["to quiet", "quiet", "quiets", "quietly"],
        "correct_answer": "quietly"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sum optimus amīcus hominis. Saepe dormiō ad pedēs dominī meī. Cum dominō ambulāre amō. Quid sum?",
        "options": ["avis", "canis", "piscis", "ursus"],
        "correct_answer": "canis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Venīte, _____, ad forum nōbīscum!",
        "options": ["Mārce et Lūcī", "fīlia mea", "mercātor", "tū"],
        "correct_answer": "Mārce et Lūcī"
    },
    {
        "question": "Aenēās Dīdōnem amat <u>sed</u> necesse est Troiānīs discēdere.",
        "options": ["and", "not", "because", "but"],
        "correct_answer": "but"
    },
    {
        "question": "To what question would the response, “Pecūnia est in saccō,” make sense?",
        "options": ["Estne pecūnia gravis?", "Ubi est pecūnia?", "Cūr pecūniam habēs?", "Quandō pecūniam invēnistī?"],
        "correct_answer": "Ubi est pecūnia?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lūcia decem rosās habet. Lūcia quattuor Cornēliae dat. Quot nunc habet Lūcia?",
        "options": ["duo", "quattuor", "sex", "octō"],
        "correct_answer": "sex"
    },
    {
        "question": "Translate: Multa animālia sunt magna saevaque.",
        "options": ["Many animals are not large or very fierce.", "Many animals are large but not fierce.", "Many animals are large and fierce.", "Many animals are neither large nor fierce."],
        "correct_answer": "Many animals are large and fierce."
    },
    {
        "question": "Super Bowl LVII was this year. Which Super Bowl was it?",
        "options": ["12", "17", "42", "57"],
        "correct_answer": "57"
    },
    {
        "question": "Students know that sometimes teachers should listen to the vōx populī. What should the teachers listen to?",
        "options": ["their own instincts", "public opinion", "the wisdom of a mentor", "their administrator’s orders"],
        "correct_answer": "public opinion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ubi gladiātōrēs imperātōrī dīcēbant, “Nōs moritūrī tē salūtāmus”?",
        "options": ["in Colossēō", "in Campō Martiō", "in Templō Iovis", "in Cūriā"],
        "correct_answer": "in Colossēō"
    },
    {
        "question": "How should Latin teachers say goodbye to their students at the end of class?",
        "options": ["Salvē!", "Salvēte!", "Valē!", "Valēte!"],
        "correct_answer": "Valē!"
    },
    {
        "question": "What name was shared by three brothers who defended Rome against the Cūriātiī of Alba Longa and by a man who defended Rome on the Pōns Sublicius from the Etruscans?",
        "options": ["Mucius", "Coriolanus", "Horatius", "Cincinnatus"],
        "correct_answer": "Horatius"
    },
    {
        "question": "Your digitī, pollex, and palma are parts of your _____.",
        "options": ["caput", "oculī", "manus", "aurēs"],
        "correct_answer": "manus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who left behind his wife Creusa as he fled from Troy with his father Anchises and son Ascanius?",
        "options": ["Priam", "Hector", "Aeneas", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "The English words effort, fortify, and comfort all derive from the same Latin adjective. What does it mean?",
        "options": ["lucky", "strong", "calm", "difficult"],
        "correct_answer": "strong"
    },
    {
        "question": "What goddess changed Actaeon into a stag that was attacked by his own hunting dogs, because he had seen her bathing in the woods?",
        "options": ["Diana", "Minerva", "Ceres", "Vesta"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ecce! Vidēs multōs amīcōs in ātriō, cibum in culīnā, hortum in peristȳliō. Ubi es?",
        "options": ["in thermīs", "in basilicā", "in vīllā", "in tabernīs"],
        "correct_answer": "in vīllā"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French word mère, the Spanish word madre, and the English word matron ultimately all derive from what Latin word?",
        "options": ["marītus", "māter", "mare", "magister"],
        "correct_answer": "māter"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to its Latin root, a creature with lupine features would resemble what animal?",
        "options": ["eagle", "horse", "fish", "wolf"],
        "correct_answer": "wolf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which room of the Roman thermae was designated for hot baths?",
        "options": ["caldārium", "tepidārium", "frīgidārium", "apodytērium"],
        "correct_answer": "caldārium"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the exile of Tarquinius Superbus and the end of the Monarchy, the Roman Republic began with Brutus and Collatinus holding which office?",
        "options": ["emperor", "dictator", "consul", "censor"],
        "correct_answer": "consul"
    },
    {
        "question": "Because the senator misspoke during their speech, they later had to correct their _______.",
        "options": ["lapsus linguae", "per capita", "nota bene", "magna cum laude"],
        "correct_answer": "lapsus linguae"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what part of a Roman house would one expect to find a garden?",
        "options": ["in culīnā", "in cubiculō", "in peristȳliō", "in tablīnō"],
        "correct_answer": "in peristȳliō"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Greek deity is often depicted with winged sandals and a snake-entwined staff called a caduceus?",
        "options": ["Hades", "Hera", "Hephaestus", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Hermes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where would a Roman boy wear his bulla?",
        "options": ["around his waist", "on his head", "around his neck", "on his finger"],
        "correct_answer": "around his neck"
    },
    {
        "question": "In addition to Pompeii, which of these cities did Mt. Vesuvius destroy?",
        "options": ["Brundisium", "Herculaneum", "Ostia", "Rome"],
        "correct_answer": "Herculaneum"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what type of contest did Arachne and Minerva participate?",
        "options": ["archery", "weaving", "running", "singing"],
        "correct_answer": "weaving"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were the chief executive officials in the government of the Roman Republic?",
        "options": ["consuls", "emperors", "kings", "priests"],
        "correct_answer": "consuls"
    },
    {
        "question": "Quot annōs habēs? is asking",
        "options": ["What day is it?", "How old are you?", "What time is it?", "Who is your mother?"],
        "correct_answer": "How old are you?"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to its Latin root, a laboratory is a place for",
        "options": ["hiding items", "washing", "working", "storing food"],
        "correct_answer": "working"
    },
    {
        "question": "One might use the Latin abbreviation ____ to restate or clarify something already mentioned.",
        "options": ["i.e.", "A.D.", "p.m.", "R.I.P."],
        "correct_answer": "i.e."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to legend, what was Cincinnatus doing when he was asked to be dictator?",
        "options": ["eating his dinner", "visiting a friend", "making a speech", "plowing a field"],
        "correct_answer": "plowing a field"
    },
    {
        "question": "Most Romans in the city of Rome did not live in vīllīs, but",
        "options": ["in thermīs", "in īnsulīs", "in templīs", "in tabernīs"],
        "correct_answer": "in īnsulīs"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Roman would typically watch a chariot race at the",
        "options": ["Curia", "Colosseum", "Circus Maximus", "Pantheon"],
        "correct_answer": "Circus Maximus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Quis sum? Sum rēx deōrum. Teneō fulmina et sceptrum. Regō omnēs et omnia.",
        "options": ["Iuppiter", "Mars", "Vulcānus", "Mercurius"],
        "correct_answer": "Iuppiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "Clāmāre, dīcere and cantāre are all verbs requiring the use of which body part?",
        "options": ["oculus", "ōs", "pēs", "manus"],
        "correct_answer": "ōs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which city was conquered using a giant wooden horse as a trick?",
        "options": ["Sparta", "Athens", "Troy", "Alexandria"],
        "correct_answer": "Troy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Innovation, novelty, and renovate all derive from the Latin word meaning",
        "options": ["make", "new", "nine", "know"],
        "correct_answer": "new"
    },
    {
        "question": "A wolf, a shepherd, a river, and a priestess are all featured in a story about",
        "options": ["Castor and Pollux", "Numa Pompilius", "Romulus and Remus", "Servius Tullius"],
        "correct_answer": "Romulus and Remus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What town, located at the mouth of the Tiber and founded by Ancus Marcius, was the port of Rome?",
        "options": ["Alba Longa", "Lavinium", "Brundisium", "Ostia"],
        "correct_answer": "Ostia"
    },
    {
        "question": "To which question would “Iūlia” be a correct response?",
        "options": ["Quid agis?", "Quāle est caelum?", "Quid est nōmen tibi?", "Ubi est lātrīna?"],
        "correct_answer": "Quid est nōmen tibi?"
    },
    {
        "question": "If Jupiter wanted to send a message, he would usually call upon",
        "options": ["Mercury", "Venus", "Mars", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Mercury"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the great, domed temple in Rome dedicated to all the gods?",
        "options": ["Circus Maximus", "Pantheon", "Campus Martius", "Palatine"],
        "correct_answer": "Pantheon"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which room of a Roman house might you find the larārium and the impluvium?",
        "options": ["trīclīnium", "cubiculum", "ātrium", "culīna"],
        "correct_answer": "ātrium"
    },
    {
        "question": "Transmission, missile, and emit are all English derivatives of the Latin verb that means to",
        "options": ["remain", "move", "warn", "send"],
        "correct_answer": "send"
    },
    {
        "question": "The abbreviation i.e. stands for the Latin words id est and is best translated",
        "options": ["that is", "for example", "therefore", "and the rest"],
        "correct_answer": "that is"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following places was NOT located on the Italian peninsula?",
        "options": ["Pompeiī", "Brundisium", "Troia", "Ōstia"],
        "correct_answer": "Troia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman god is often represented by a statue of a long-haired youth with a lyre or a bow and a quiver of arrows?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Mars", "Mercury", "Vulcan"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin words Novus ordō seclōrum, found on a U.S. dollar bill, may be translated",
        "options": ["Out of many one", "New order of the ages", "He has favored our beginnings", "In God we trust"],
        "correct_answer": "New order of the ages"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is the year 1976 expressed in Roman numerals?",
        "options": ["MCMLXXVI", "MMLX", "MCMVI", "MMXII"],
        "correct_answer": "MCMLXXVI"
    },
    {
        "question": "If a Latin student answers, “Adsum,” what does the teacher understand?",
        "options": ["everyone is ready", "someone is sick", "the student is late", "the student is present"],
        "correct_answer": "the student is present"
    },
    {
        "question": "Iēntāculum, prandium, and cēna are Latin words that refer to",
        "options": ["a woman’s clothes", "architecture", "meals", "rooms of a house"],
        "correct_answer": "meals"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Roman history, Romulus, Numa, Tullus Hostilius, and Tarquinius Priscus were",
        "options": ["consuls", "emperors", "generals", "kings"],
        "correct_answer": "kings"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Roman numeral LIX represents the number:",
        "options": ["29", "59", "69", "109"],
        "correct_answer": "59"
    },
    {
        "question": "What structure in ancient Rome was used for chariot racing?",
        "options": ["Pantheon", "Curia", "Basilica", "Circus"],
        "correct_answer": "Circus"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a Roman matron left the house, she would cover her head and shoulders with a:",
        "options": ["palla", "solea", "tunica", "bulla"],
        "correct_answer": "palla"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pompeii, Herculaneum, and Stabiae were all destroyed:",
        "options": ["during the 2nd Punic War", "by the fire of A.D. 64", "in an invasion by the Gauls", "by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79"],
        "correct_answer": "by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79"
    },
    {
        "question": "His bird was the eagle, his tree was the oak. He punished mortals with his lightning bolt. Who was he?",
        "options": ["Ares", "Zeus", "Hermes", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Zeus"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Roman merchant would have navigated down the Tiber River in order to set sail from the port of:",
        "options": ["Carthage", "Ostia", "Pompeii", "Brundisium"],
        "correct_answer": "Ostia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Quis erat deus bellī et pater Rōmulī Remīque?",
        "options": ["Mars", "Iuppiter", "Neptūnus", "Vulcānus"],
        "correct_answer": "Mars"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ad astra per aspera and Labor omnia vincit are Latin sayings that encourage the value of:",
        "options": ["being honest", "showing kindness", "working hard", "being humble"],
        "correct_answer": "working hard"
    },
    {
        "question": "The English words regal, regent, and regime all derive from the Latin verb meaning:",
        "options": ["plow", "rule", "build", "read"],
        "correct_answer": "rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "After 20 minutes of playing _____ with his classmates, the Latin student had to call out 'Ubi estis? Nōn possum vōs invenīre! Redīte ad mē!'",
        "options": ["soccer", "basketball", "hide-and-seek", "tag"],
        "correct_answer": "hide-and-seek"
    },
    {
        "question": "The common Latin abbreviation P.S. stands for",
        "options": ["per silvās", "post scientiam", "per stylum", "post scrīptum"],
        "correct_answer": "post scrīptum"
    },
    {
        "question": "If your classmate asks you, 'Quota hōra est?' he wants to know",
        "options": ["what time it is", "how you are doing", "how many friends you have", "what the weather is"],
        "correct_answer": "what time it is"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus was elected chairman of the board in absentia.",
        "options": ["although youthful", "although inexperienced", "although not present", "although not interested in the position"],
        "correct_answer": "although not present"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Roman senator would most likely wear a ____when out in public.",
        "options": ["stola", "toga", "bulla", "palla"],
        "correct_answer": "toga"
    },
    {
        "question": "A cubiculum, culīna, and trīclīnium were found",
        "options": ["in aquā", "in caelō", "in templō", "in vīllā"],
        "correct_answer": "in vīllā"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin abbreviation P.M. (post merīdiem) means",
        "options": ["dawn", "morning", "noon", "afternoon"],
        "correct_answer": "afternoon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the Roman name for the god of the sea?",
        "options": ["Neptune", "Mars", "Apollo", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Neptune"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman structure was primarily used for chariot races?",
        "options": ["the Forum", "the Pantheon", "the Circus Maximus", "the Colosseum"],
        "correct_answer": "the Circus Maximus"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin phrase 'Veni, vidi, vici' translates to",
        "options": ["I came, I saw, I conquered", "I went, I fought, I won", "I arrived, I watched, I succeeded", "I entered, I fought, I overcame"],
        "correct_answer": "I came, I saw, I conquered"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman numeral is used to represent the number 50?",
        "options": ["L", "C", "D", "M"],
        "correct_answer": "L"
    },
    {
        "question": "In ancient Rome, what was a 'toga'?",
        "options": ["a type of food", "a piece of clothing", "a musical instrument", "a kind of building"],
        "correct_answer": "a piece of clothing"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the Roman goddess of love and beauty?",
        "options": ["Juno", "Minerva", "Venus", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the primary language spoken in ancient Rome?",
        "options": ["Greek", "Latin", "Hebrew", "Aramaic"],
        "correct_answer": "Latin"
    },
    {
        "question": "The phrase 'Caveat emptor' means",
        "options": ["let the buyer beware", "let the seller be honest", "buy now, pay later", "none of the above"],
        "correct_answer": "let the buyer beware"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the Roman god of war?",
        "options": ["Neptune", "Mars", "Apollo", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Mars"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman festival was celebrated in honor of the god Saturn?",
        "options": ["Saturnalia", "Lupercalia", "Consualia", "Floralia"],
        "correct_answer": "Saturnalia"
    },
    {
        "question": "In ancient Rome, a 'villa' was",
        "options": ["a type of meal", "a kind of weapon", "a large country house", "a type of festival"],
        "correct_answer": "a large country house"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman numeral is used to represent the number 100?",
        "options": ["L", "C", "D", "M"],
        "correct_answer": "C"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin phrase 'Et tu, Brute?' translates to",
        "options": ["And you, Brutus?", "What is it, Brutus?", "Why, Brutus?", "Hello, Brutus!"],
        "correct_answer": "And you, Brutus?"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the purpose of the Roman 'Forum'?",
        "options": ["a place for gladiatorial games", "a marketplace and public square", "a residential area", "a military training ground"],
        "correct_answer": "a marketplace and public square"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the Roman goddess of the hunt?",
        "options": ["Minerva", "Venus", "Diana", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these Roman buildings was used for religious ceremonies?",
        "options": ["the Colosseum", "the Circus Maximus", "the Pantheon", "the Forum"],
        "correct_answer": "the Pantheon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the Latin phrase 'Ad astra' mean?",
        "options": ["to the stars", "to the earth", "through the heavens", "from the heavens"],
        "correct_answer": "to the stars"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the first emperor of Rome?",
        "options": ["Augustus", "Nero", "Julius Caesar", "Trajan"],
        "correct_answer": "Augustus"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin word 'aqua' means",
        "options": ["fire", "air", "water", "earth"],
        "correct_answer": "water"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Roman building is known for its large dome and oculus?",
        "options": ["the Colosseum", "the Forum", "the Pantheon", "the Circus Maximus"],
        "correct_answer": "the Pantheon"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Latin phrase 'Tempus fugit' means",
        "options": ["time flies", "time stands still", "time is precious", "time is slow"],
        "correct_answer": "time flies"
    },
    {
        "question": "ego, mei",
        "options": ["I, me", "you (sg.)", "we, us", "you (pl.), you all"],
        "correct_answer": "I, me"
      },
      {
        "question": "tū, tuī",
        "options": ["I, me", "you (sg.)", "we, us", "you (pl.), you all"],
        "correct_answer": "you (sg.)"
      },
      {
        "question": "nōs, nostrī/nostrum",
        "options": ["I, me", "you (sg.)", "we, us", "you (pl.), you all"],
        "correct_answer": "we, us"
      },
      {
        "question": "vōs, vestrī/vestrum",
        "options": ["I, me", "you (sg.)", "we, us", "you (pl.), you all"],
        "correct_answer": "you (pl.), you all"
      },
      {
        "question": "suī, sibi, sē, sē",
        "options": ["him/her/it/one's-self; themselves", "this; these (pl.)", "that; those (pl.)", "himself/herself/itself; the very/real/actual one"],
        "correct_answer": "him/her/it/one's-self; themselves"
      },
      {
        "question": "hic, haec, hoc",
        "options": ["him/her/it/one's-self; themselves", "this; these (pl.)", "that; those (pl.)", "himself/herself/itself; the very/real/actual one"],
        "correct_answer": "this; these (pl.)"
      },
      {
        "question": "ille, illa, illud",
        "options": ["him/her/it/one's-self; themselves", "this; these (pl.)", "that; those (pl.)", "himself/herself/itself; the very/real/actual one"],
        "correct_answer": "that; those (pl.)"
      },
      {
        "question": "ipse, ipsa, ipsum",
        "options": ["him/her/it/one's-self; themselves", "this; these (pl.)", "that; those (pl.)", "himself/herself/itself; the very/real/actual one"],
        "correct_answer": "himself/herself/itself; the very/real/actual one"
      },
      {
        "question": "is, ea, id",
        "options": ["he/she/it/they (by gender/number)", "who, which, that", "Behold!", "Alas!"],
        "correct_answer": "he/she/it/they (by gender/number)"
      },
      {
        "question": "quī, quae, quod",
        "options": ["he/she/it/they (by gender/number)", "who, which, that", "Behold!", "Alas!"],
        "correct_answer": "who, which, that"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ecce!",
        "options": ["Behold!", "Alas!", "Oh, good! Well done!", "Yes (indeed)!"],
        "correct_answer": "Behold!"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ēheu!",
        "options": ["Behold!", "Alas!", "Oh, good! Well done!", "Yes (indeed)!"],
        "correct_answer": "Alas!"
      },
      {
        "question": "Euge!",
        "options": ["Behold!", "Alas!", "Oh, good! Well done!", "Yes (indeed)!"],
        "correct_answer": "Oh, good! Well done!"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ita (vērō)",
        "options": ["Behold!", "Alas!", "Oh, good! Well done!", "Yes (indeed)!"],
        "correct_answer": "Yes (indeed)!"
      },
      {
        "question": "Minimē!",
        "options": ["No!", "Why?", "How?", "How many?"],
        "correct_answer": "No!"
      },
      {
        "question": "Cūr?",
        "options": ["No!", "Why?", "How?", "How many?"],
        "correct_answer": "Why?"
      },
      {
        "question": "-ne (enclitic)",
        "options": ["(expects yes or no answer)", "(expects yes answer)", "(expects no answer)", "(of)?"],
        "correct_answer": "(expects yes or no answer)"
      },
      {
        "question": "Nōnne?",
        "options": ["(expects yes or no answer)", "(expects yes answer)", "(expects no answer)", "(of)?"],
        "correct_answer": "(expects yes answer)"
      },
      {
        "question": "Num?",
        "options": ["(expects yes or no answer)", "(expects yes answer)", "(expects no answer)", "(of)?"],
        "correct_answer": "(expects no answer)"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quālis?, Quāle?",
        "options": ["What kind/sort (of)?", "When?", "What?", "Who?"],
        "correct_answer": "What kind/sort (of)?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quandō?",
        "options": ["What kind/sort (of)?", "When?", "What?", "Who?"],
        "correct_answer": "When?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quid?",
        "options": ["What kind/sort (of)?", "When?", "What?", "Who?"],
        "correct_answer": "What?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quis?",
        "options": ["What kind/sort (of)?", "When?", "What?", "Who?"],
        "correct_answer": "Who?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quō?",
        "options": ["To where?", "How?", "How many?", "Where?"],
        "correct_answer": "To where?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quōmodo?",
        "options": ["To where?", "How?", "How many?", "Where?"],
        "correct_answer": "How?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Quot?",
        "options": ["To where?", "How?", "How many?", "Where?"],
        "correct_answer": "How many?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ubi?",
        "options": ["To where?", "How?", "How many?", "Where?"],
        "correct_answer": "Where?"
      },
      {
        "question": "Unde?",
        "options": ["To where?", "How?", "How many?", "From where?"],
        "correct_answer": "From where?"
      },
      {
        "question": "ad (+acc)",
        "options": ["to, towards; at, near", "before, in front of", "at, near, among; at the house of", "around"],
        "correct_answer": "to, towards; at, near"
      },
      {
        "question": "ante (+acc)",
        "options": ["to, towards; at, near", "before, in front of", "at, near, among; at the house of", "around"],
        "correct_answer": "before, in front of"
      },
      {
        "question": "apud (+acc)",
        "options": ["to, towards; at, near", "before, in front of", "at, near, among; at the house of", "around"],
        "correct_answer": "at, near, among; at the house of"
      },
      {
        "question": "circum (+acc)",
        "options": ["to, towards; at, near", "before, in front of", "at, near, among; at the house of", "around"],
        "correct_answer": "around"
      },
      {
        "question": "contrā (+acc)",
        "options": ["against", "outside of", "below", "between, among"],
        "correct_answer": "against"
      },
      {
        "question": "extrā (+acc)",
        "options": ["against", "outside of", "below", "between, among"],
        "correct_answer": "outside of"
      },
      {
        "question": "infrā (+acc)",
        "options": ["against", "outside of", "below", "between, among"],
        "correct_answer": "below"
      },
      {
        "question": "inter (+acc)",
        "options": ["against", "outside of", "below", "between, among"],
        "correct_answer": "between, among"
      },
      {
        "question": "intrā (+acc)",
        "options": ["within, inside", "because of", "through", "behind, after"],
        "correct_answer": "within, inside"
      },
      {
        "question": "ob (+acc)",
        "options": ["within, inside", "because of", "through", "behind, after"],
        "correct_answer": "because of"
      },
      {
        "question": "per (+acc)",
        "options": ["within, inside", "because of", "through", "behind, after"],
        "correct_answer": "through"
      },
      {
        "question": "post (+acc)",
        "options": ["within, inside", "because of", "through", "behind, after"],
        "correct_answer": "behind, after"
      },
      {
        "question": "praeter (+acc)",
        "options": ["except, beyond", "near", "on account of", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "except, beyond"
      },
      {
        "question": "prope (+acc)",
        "options": ["except, beyond", "near", "on account of", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "near"
      },
      {
        "question": "propter (+acc)",
        "options": ["except, beyond", "near", "on account of", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "on account of"
      },
      {
        "question": "suprā (+acc)",
        "options": ["except, beyond", "near", "on account of", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "above, over"
      },
      {
        "question": "trāns (+acc)",
        "options": ["across", "beyond", "away from, from", "with"],
        "correct_answer": "across"
      },
      {
        "question": "ultrā (+acc)",
        "options": ["across", "beyond", "away from, from", "with"],
        "correct_answer": "beyond"
      },
      {
        "question": "ā / ab (+abl)",
        "options": ["away from, from; (with time words) since; (with passive voice) by", "with", "down from, from; about", "out of, from"],
        "correct_answer": "away from, from; (with time words) since; (with passive voice) by"
      },
      {
        "question": "cum (+abl)",
        "options": ["away from, from; (with time words) since; (with passive voice) by", "with", "down from, from; about", "out of, from"],
        "correct_answer": "with"
      },
      {
        "question": "dē (+abl)",
        "options": ["away from, from; (with time words) since; (with passive voice) by", "with", "down from, from; about", "out of, from"],
        "correct_answer": "down from, from; about"
      },
      {
        "question": "ē / ex (+abl)",
        "options": ["away from, from; (with time words) since; (with passive voice) by", "with", "down from, from; about", "out of, from"],
        "correct_answer": "out of, from"
      },
      {
        "question": "prae (+abl)",
        "options": ["for, in front of, on behalf of", "without", "before, in front of", "from"],
        "correct_answer": "before, in front of"
      },
      {
        "question": "prō (+abl)",
        "options": ["for, in front of, on behalf of", "without", "before, in front of", "from"],
        "correct_answer": "for, in front of, on behalf of"
      },
      {
        "question": "sine (+abl)",
        "options": ["for, in front of, on behalf of", "without", "before, in front of", "from"],
        "correct_answer": "without"
      },
      {
        "question": "in (+acc. with verbs of motion)",
        "options": ["into, onto, against", "in, on, upon", "under, beneath", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "into, onto, against"
      },
      {
        "question": "sub (+acc. with verbs of motion)",
        "options": ["into, onto, against", "in, on, upon", "under, beneath", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "under, beneath"
      },
      {
        "question": "super (+acc. with verbs of motion)",
        "options": ["into, onto, against", "in, on, upon", "under, beneath", "above, over"],
        "correct_answer": "above, over"
      },
      {
        "question": "atque or ac",
        "options": ["and, and also, and moreover", "but, but on the other hand", "or", "either...or"],
        "correct_answer": "and, and also, and moreover"
      },
      {
        "question": "at",
        "options": ["and, and also, and moreover", "but, but on the other hand", "or", "either...or"],
        "correct_answer": "but, but on the other hand"
      },
      {
        "question": "aut",
        "options": ["and, and also, and moreover", "but, but on the other hand", "or", "either...or"],
        "correct_answer": "or"
      },
      {
        "question": "aut...aut",
        "options": ["and, and also, and moreover", "but, but on the other hand", "or", "either...or"],
        "correct_answer": "either...or"
      },
      {
        "question": "autem (postpositive)",
        "options": ["however, but, moreover, also", "therefore", "nor, and not", "neither...nor"],
        "correct_answer": "however, but, moreover, also"
      },
      {
        "question": "dum",
        "options": ["however, but, moreover, also", "therefore", "nor, and not", "neither...nor"],
        "correct_answer": "while"
      },
      {
        "question": "enim (postpositive)",
        "options": ["however, but, moreover, also", "therefore", "for, because, indeed, truly", "nor, and not"],
        "correct_answer": "for, because, indeed, truly"
      },
      {
        "question": "et",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "both...and"],
        "correct_answer": "and"
      },
      {
        "question": "et...et",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "both...and"],
        "correct_answer": "both...and"
      },
      {
        "question": "igitur (postpositive)",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "therefore"],
        "correct_answer": "therefore"
      },
      {
        "question": "nam",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "for, because"],
        "correct_answer": "for, because"
      },
      {
        "question": "nec or neque",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "for, because"],
        "correct_answer": "nor, and not"
      },
      {
        "question": "neque...neque",
        "options": ["and", "nor, and not", "neither...nor", "for, because"],
        "correct_answer": "neither...nor"
      },
      {
        "question": "postquam",
        "options": ["after", "although", "and also", "because"],
        "correct_answer": "after"
      },
      {
        "question": "quamquam",
        "options": ["after", "although", "and also", "because"],
        "correct_answer": "although"
      },
      {
        "question": "-que (enclitic)",
        "options": ["and", "but", "or", "however"],
        "correct_answer": "and"
      },
      {
        "question": "quod",
        "options": ["and", "but", "or", "because"],
        "correct_answer": "because"
      },
      {
        "question": "sed",
        "options": ["and", "but", "or", "because"],
        "correct_answer": "but"
      },
      {
        "question": "ubi",
        "options": ["where, when", "how", "what", "why"],
        "correct_answer": "where, when"
      },
      {
        "question": "ūnus, ūna, ūnum",
        "options": ["one", "two", "three", "four"],
        "correct_answer": "one"
      },
      {
        "question": "duo, duae, duo",
        "options": ["one", "two", "three", "four"],
        "correct_answer": "two"
      },
      {
        "question": "trēs, trēs, tria",
        "options": ["one", "two", "three", "four"],
        "correct_answer": "three"
      },
      {
        "question": "quattuor",
        "options": ["four", "five", "six", "seven"],
        "correct_answer": "four"
      },
      {
        "question": "quīnque",
        "options": ["four", "five", "six", "seven"],
        "correct_answer": "five"
      },
      {
        "question": "sex",
        "options": ["five", "six", "seven", "eight"],
        "correct_answer": "six"
      },
      {
        "question": "septem",
        "options": ["six", "seven", "eight", "nine"],
        "correct_answer": "seven"
      },
      {
        "question": "octō",
        "options": ["seven", "eight", "nine", "ten"],
        "correct_answer": "eight"
      },
      {
        "question": "novem",
        "options": ["eight", "nine", "ten", "eleven"],
        "correct_answer": "nine"
      },
      {
        "question": "decem",
        "options": ["nine", "ten", "eleven", "twelve"],
        "correct_answer": "ten"
      },
      {
        "question": "ūndecim",
        "options": ["ten", "eleven", "twelve", "thirteen"],
        "correct_answer": "eleven"
      },
      {
        "question": "duodecim",
        "options": ["eleven", "twelve", "thirteen", "fourteen"],
        "correct_answer": "twelve"
      },
      {
        "question": "tredecim",
        "options": ["twelve", "thirteen", "fourteen", "fifteen"],
        "correct_answer": "thirteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "quattuordecim",
        "options": ["thirteen", "fourteen", "fifteen", "sixteen"],
        "correct_answer": "fourteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "quīndecim",
        "options": ["fourteen", "fifteen", "sixteen", "seventeen"],
        "correct_answer": "fifteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "sēdecim",
        "options": ["fifteen", "sixteen", "seventeen", "eighteen"],
        "correct_answer": "sixteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "septendecim",
        "options": ["sixteen", "seventeen", "eighteen", "nineteen"],
        "correct_answer": "seventeen"
      },
      {
        "question": "duodēvīgintī",
        "options": ["seventeen", "eighteen", "nineteen", "twenty"],
        "correct_answer": "eighteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "undēvīgintī",
        "options": ["eighteen", "nineteen", "twenty", "twenty-one"],
        "correct_answer": "nineteen"
      },
      {
        "question": "vīgintī",
        "options": ["nineteen", "twenty", "twenty-one", "one hundred"],
        "correct_answer": "twenty"
      },
      {
        "question": "vīgintī et ūnus",
        "options": ["twenty", "twenty-one", "one hundred", "one thousand"],
        "correct_answer": "twenty-one"
      },
      {
        "question": "centum",
        "options": ["twenty-one", "one hundred", "one thousand", "first"],
        "correct_answer": "one hundred"
      },
      {
        "question": "mīlle",
        "options": ["one hundred", "one thousand", "first", "second"],
        "correct_answer": "one thousand"
      },
      {
        "question": "prīmus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["one thousand", "first", "second", "third"],
        "correct_answer": "first"
      },
      {
        "question": "secundus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["first", "second", "third", "fourth"],
        "correct_answer": "second"
      },
      {
        "question": "tertius, -a, -um",
        "options": ["second", "third", "fourth", "fifth"],
        "correct_answer": "third"
      },
      {
        "question": "quārtus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["third", "fourth", "fifth", "sixth"],
        "correct_answer": "fourth"
      },
      {
        "question": "quīntus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["fourth", "fifth", "sixth", "seventh"],
        "correct_answer": "fifth"
      },
      {
        "question": "sextus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["fifth", "sixth", "seventh", "eighth"],
        "correct_answer": "sixth"
      },
      {
        "question": "septimus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["sixth", "seventh", "eighth", "ninth"],
        "correct_answer": "seventh"
      },
      {
        "question": "octāvus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["seventh", "eighth", "ninth", "tenth"],
        "correct_answer": "eighth"
      },
      {
        "question": "nōnus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["eighth", "ninth", "tenth", "eleventh"],
        "correct_answer": "ninth"
      },
      {
        "question": "decimus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["ninth", "tenth", "eleventh", "twelfth"],
        "correct_answer": "tenth"
      },
      {
        "question": "ūndecimus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["tenth", "eleventh", "twelfth", "thirteenth"],
        "correct_answer": "eleventh"
      },
      {
        "question": "duodecimus, -a, -um",
        "options": ["eleventh", "twelfth", "thirteenth", "fourteenth"],
        "correct_answer": "twelfth"
      }
    ]
  }
  